<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>The Drunkard forewarned and the swearer caution'd in a late judgement on the body of Dowee Sitses sent in a letter from Theodorus Paludamus ... to the Lady Habuerin : published for the information of some, and premonition to others, to lead a more pious life.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1682</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 8 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 5 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2014-11">2014-11 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A36575</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing D2205_VARIANT</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R24300</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">08119079</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 08119079</idno>
            <idno type="VID">40886</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online text creation partnership.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A36575)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 40886)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1228:3)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>The Drunkard forewarned and the swearer caution'd in a late judgement on the body of Dowee Sitses sent in a letter from Theodorus Paludamus ... to the Lady Habuerin : published for the information of some, and premonition to others, to lead a more pious life.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>6 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed for William Sceates,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1682.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in the Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Temperance (Virtue)</term>
               <term>Cardinal virtues.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-07</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-05</date>
            <label>Mona Logarbo</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2014-03</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:40886:1"/>
            <p>THE <hi>Drunkard Forewarn'd,</hi> AND THE SWEARER CAUTION'D, IN A LATE JUDGEMENT On the Body of Dowee Sitſes: Sent in a LETTER from <hi>Theodorus Paludamus</hi> Publick Preacher at <hi>Lewar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>den</hi> in <hi>Frizeland,</hi> to the Lady <hi>Habuerin.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>Publiſhed for the Information of ſome, and Premonition to others, to Lead a more Pious Life.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed for <hi>William Sceates</hi> in <hi>Three-Dia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mond-Court</hi> in <hi>Hoſier<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>Lane.</hi> 1682.</p>
            <pb facs="tcp:40886:2"/>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:40886:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A True Copy of a Letter from</hi> Theodorus Paludamus, <hi>Publick Preacher at</hi> Lewarden <hi>in</hi> Frizeland, <hi>to the Lady</hi> Habuerin.</head>
            <p>THe buſineſs of <hi>Dowee Sitſes</hi> Maſon of <hi>Bolſworth,</hi> was after this manner: I and others at <hi>Lewarden</hi> hearing the Reports mixed with many Fabulous things, gave little Credit to it: Whereupon the other day the Lord Procuror-general (to whom I am Uncle) came to me, and told me, he had an Order from the Lords of the Provincial-Court, to go and take an Information of the matter; and deſired me for the Strangeneſs thereof to go along with him, that we might be Eye Witneſſes there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of: I did willingly take hold of the opportunity offered me; we came there in the Evening, and in the Morning, when the Patient was to be Dreſt, we went to him, where we found two Maſter Chyrurgions, and their two Servants, buſie in making Plaiſters and Dreſſing the Patient, and he in ſuch a Lamentable Condition, as we could not behold but with Amazement; his Hair Burnt off
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:40886:3"/> his Head to his Ears; his whole Face Burnt except his Eyes, which were ſcarce hurt; his Armes Burnt in ſeveral places; his Hands to t<gap reason="illegible" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>e very end of his Fingers, were like a Foot of a Roaſted Fowl, but could move all his Fingers; his Breaſt Burnt in ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veral places, and alſo his Back, but one ſide more than the other, though the Chyrurgions declared that his Shirt was whole; His Belly under the Navel, for about the breadth of a Hand, was as Black as a Stock in which place the Chyrurgions made ſeveral Inciſions, and he felt it not; his Privi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties were in like manner: My Lady, you muſt forgive me, that I Write thus Homely; only am minded to give your Ladyſhip a perfect Account of the matter. Further, his Hips, Thighs and Legs were Lamentably Burnt, although his Stockings were on and Tyed; when the Chyrurgions came to him, and one Stocking was whole, except a little Hole in the Calf, but that Leg was moſt Burnt; the Chyrurgions declared alſo that his Shirt Sleeves were whole; his Feet alſo were Burnt. And in ſhort, I know not one part of him that was free; I look'd narrowly into all, and a Loathſome and Lamentable ſight it was. I went to the Woman <hi>Hoyck Ankies,</hi> who gave me a ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtantial Account of all the circumſtances, and alſo
<pb n="3" facs="tcp:40886:3"/> her Husband; the Patient alſo after he was Dreſt, and had layna while and got a little Breath, gave us a full Account of the Paſſages, with whom I willingly ſpoke, partly for the ſtirring up of his Soul, and partly to have a certain Teſtimony of things concerning him, though it was hard for him to ſpeak by reaſon of his weakneſs; all which In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation the Lord Procuror-general took upon Oath from the Patient himſelf, from his Wife, and the Chyrurgions, and all agreed as one perſon in the Relation.</p>
            <p>The thing was thus, upon the 15/25 of <hi>June</hi> laſt at Evening, this <hi>Dowee Sitſes</hi> came Drunk into the Houſe of <hi>Ruward Ipes Wigerſure,</hi> a Tavern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>keeper, where he with the man of the Houſe, and one <hi>Albert Roloofes,</hi> Drank 3 Quarts of Wine: And about half an Hour paſt Ten, his Daughter-in-Law came to call him, and he went home with her; and his Wife and he having been ſeveral days fallen out, he went into the Kitchin and lay down to Sleep upon the Cuſhions, and fell in a Dream about a Story he had Read in a Book of <hi>Simon De <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ries,</hi> of a certain Company that had Danced in Maſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>querade, with every one a Lighted Torch in their Hand, wherewith they Burnt one another; where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon he waked and ſtood up, thinking to go in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:40886:4"/> the Yard to make Water, and of a ſudden he found himſelf of a Light-flame in the midſt of the Room, which Burnt him and a great part of his Cloaths ſo Lamentably, without ſeeing or hear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing any thing but the Flame: While this Burning laſted he cryed out for help, but none came; then he began to Faint, and in his Diſtreſs cryed out, <hi>Oh! God be Gracious unto me a poor Sinner,</hi> and thereupon the Flame ceaſed in the twinkling of an Eye; but he grew Fainter and Fainter, and laid his Head upon a Cuſhion in a Corner of the Kitchin.</p>
            <p>About Two in the Morning his Wife looked through a Glaſs-Window to ſee for her Husband, but being dark ſhe could not ſee him; ſhe opened the Door and went into the Kitchin, where ſhe found him in this miſerable Condition, and as ſhe went, ſhe felt ſomething under her Feet, which after ſhe got a Light, ſhe found to be a Parcel of Red<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>aſhes, and Burnt-Rags, and Steping to her Husband, ſhe took hold of his Sleeve, and had only a Burnt piece thereof in her hand; whereupon ſhe cryes out, <hi>Oh Lord!</hi> Dowee, <hi>Thou art grievouſly Burnt:</hi> He Anſwered, <hi>The Devil hath brought me into this Caſe:</hi> She being amazed, called in the Neighbours, who were all aſtoniſhed, and brought the Chyrurgions, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <pb n="5" facs="tcp:40886:4"/>
            <p> He had a <hi>Bombazine-</hi>Coat with <hi>Braſs-</hi>Buttons, which is quite Burnt up, Buttons and all, and no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing of it can be found; the Tin Buttons of his Waſtcoat are Melted, and lay there in little crooked bits and pieces upon the Floor: I had four or five pieces of them, I preſerved two of them, and gave the Lord Procuror-general the other. I was in the Kitchin, and in the midſt of the Floor where he ſtood; there are ſeveral of the Pavements as black as a Hearth that had Fire kept a good while upon it; but though the Kitchin was very Low, there was nothing to be ſeen of the Fire, one Cuſhion where he had lain, had a little Hole Burnt in it; the Neighbours found the Fire on the Hearth well covered up, and lay with White Aſhes on it; the Aſhes that lay on the Floor were Red, which might come off of his Coat that was Burnt. One of the Chyrurgions finding him thus Burnt, and that in an Unburnt Shirt and Stockins; ſaid to him, <hi>This is no Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tural Fire;</hi> to which he Anſwered, <hi>Without doubt it was not.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>His Wife ſaid, ſhe had cauſed their Miniſters to reprove him for his Drunkenneſs, but it had been in vain; ſo that the ſaying of <hi>Solomon</hi> is made true in him, <hi>A man that is often Reproved</hi>
               <pb n="6" facs="tcp:40886:5"/> 
               <hi>and hardens his Neck, ſhall ſuddenly be broken, and there ſhall be no Healing.</hi> His Wife ſaid alſo, that he had been very much given to Drink <hi>Brandy</hi> and other Strong Liquor, and that he had often with Oathes bound himſelf from it, yet fell into it again; his manner of words were, <hi>That if he were Drunk again with it, he wiſh'd the Devil might Tear him Limb from Limb:</hi> So that God hath made uſe of the Devil as an Executioner of his Judg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to bring the miſerable mans own Curſe upon him, not one Limb or Member is left whole upon him.</p>
            <p>Surely it is a fearful Judgment of God, by which all Drunkards, Curſers, and all Ungodly men may ſee much: What it was that did it I cannot tell, for the Fire on the Hearth was ſafe covered; Lightning there was none in the Country that night; <hi>Brandy</hi> could not burn his Cloathes, ſo God knows how it came, we may wonder at it, but cannot find any Natural Cauſe. So I have given your Ladyſhip an Account of the Circumſtances in Anſwer to your deſire, according to my Ability, and commit you to Gods Grace, wiſhing you all manner of Health and Bleſſings, and am your Servant in the Lord,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Theodorus Paludamus</hi> Eccleſ. <hi>Lewarden.</hi>
               </signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
